After Andrey Karpathy tweeted about
Context Engineering, AI World has
become very popular as a new
buzzword.
How popular it has become is that
the Cognition team directly said
that to build AI agents,
Context Engineering is the number
one skill that everyone needs to
have.
What is Context Engineering?
Is Prompt Engineering very different
or is it a new concept altogether?
In this video, I will give you a
very simple example of Context
Engineering and explain it very
neatly and cleanly.
By the end of this video,
you will have the knowledge on what
is Context Engineering and why it is
important for building AI agents and
how is it different from Prompt
Engineering.
So without any delay, let's get
started.
So first topic, is Prompt
Engineering really dead?
No guys, Prompt Engineering has not
gone anywhere.
So we write prompts, right?
Those prompts are 10 % of the job.
So in 2022 and 2025,
when we have all of these ChatGPT
events, people are focused upon how
to write better prompts to get
better outputs.
In 2025, we have something called as
MCPs, tools, how to get better
context.
So what happened in 2025 and 2026 is
that Prompt Engineering is a very
prominent role, but it is only 10 %
of what we are going to give it to
the LLM to get our job done.
So Prompt Engineering is not dead
anywhere. It is just absorbed into a
bigger context.
So before understanding what Context
Engineering is, let's quickly recap
how to write prompts.
So we have five different steps.
One is role, the other is context,
task, format and length.
By using all these formats,
you will write a better prompt,
so that you get a better output.
If you don't understand all of these
things, please watch my previous
video, which is about the Prompt
Engineering Masterclass.
Now what we are going to do is,
now let's look at how an LLM works
usually.
So what happens to us?
If we have the text tokens,
those tokens will go to LLM and LLM
will give you the output.
So where do these tokens come from?
From the prompt that we have
written. Yes or no? And this is our
output.
So this is how a basic ChatGPT or
something like that works.
So everything that you are going to
get as an output is being passed as
a question in the prompt.
That is what we call it as a prompt
engineering.
Otherwise, now everything is
regarding agents. Yes or no?
So what happens is, we have tokens,
you call LLM and you get output.
But this is not the way that the
current industry is going towards.
Now what will you do? You will
directly interact with an agent.
Now what will this agent do?
It will go and talk to the LLM.
It will take the output back and
this agent will give you the output.
Otherwise, this agent is doing this
call autonomously by itself.
Here you are not deciding what is
the prompt that you are going to get
into the LLM.
Rather, an agent is deciding which
prompt to give it to LLM such that
it can achieve the task.
Let's say you have a travel agent.
What is the job of that travel
agent?
Let's take an example of what kind
of tickets to book if you want to go
from Rajahmundry to Kakinada.
So what does the first agent do?
It will look at the distance between
Rajahmundry to Kakinada.
After that, it will also look at the
options we have, bus, train,
car, anything.
After that, it will try to book the
tickets.
To book the tickets, you need some
connection details, right?
So how is this agent going to get
those things?
That is where we have something
called as tools and MCPs.
What are these tools and MCPs?
It is how an agent should work in a
very specific manner.
That is what we are defining in
these two things.
We will learn about these things in
detail later on, so don't worry.
So now, this agent will work
properly by having all of these as
an input, but not only as a prompt.
If you write the entire travel agent
in a single prompt, do you think
that is going to work properly?
Definitely not.
We are talking about only one agent,
but what if there are multiple
agents?
What will you do then?
Then that is the problem where a
prompt engineering is facing.
So that is where the context
engineering comes into picture.
Then why is it called context?
Do you know what context is?
If you haven't seen my tokens video,
please go ahead and watch it.
Every model has a limit on how much
information it can process.
And that is what we call it as a
context.
Now, if we fill in the context of an
LLM, we get
better output from the agents.
That is exactly what we are going to
learn in context engineering.
Now let's look at what are all the
topics that we can fill inside this
context window.
So there are six things majorly that
we will put inside the context
window.
The first thing is the user message.
What is your question?
Let's say I want to book a ticket
from Rajahmundry to Kakinada.
That is what a user message is.
After that, we have something called
a system prompt.
In prompt engineering,
whenever you put a prompt,
it will do the prompt engineering by
using something called a system
prompt.
So we also have to write this
So even that is present inside the
context window.
And after that, there is something
called as tools.
What tools are used to do a task?
Let's say I want to create a PDF.
So to create a PDF, I need
to use some packages like vzprint
and Pymu PDF.
So what we will do is,
in these tools, we will say,
if the user wants to have a PDF
generated,
we will use these packages.
Those are what we call it as tools.
So by doing this, LLM doesn't think
too much about it
and it will follow the pattern that
we decided.
And there is the next thing which is
called resources.
To achieve this task,
what is the information that you are
going to provide to LLM?
That is what resources are.
Usually, I have written all this in
the same size,
but resources are very big.
So let's say you want an LLM to
automatically convert your text into
SQL.
To convert your text into SQL,
the LLM needs to have access to the
whole schema of the tables,
databases, every single thing,
right?
Then only it can properly map
to which table you want to join or
query.
Then it can do it properly.
So this is the major stuff.
It is like the complete information
that is needed for the LLM
to achieve the task that you are
providing.
And after that, we have something
called as assistant history.
What is this?
Let's say you are talking to an
agent,
and the agent is doing some work,
so all of that information needs to
be documented somewhere,
right?
All that information will lie inside
assistant history.
And after that, we have something
called as tool call history.
That is, when you asked them to do
PDF,
you mentioned to use vzprint or
PyMuPDF.
Then what will the agent do?
They will go and talk to those
packages
and it will do the execution.
Then what is the output?
All of that information is being
captured into tool call history.
Then in a context window like
ChatGPT, Grok, LLM,
there will be only one prompt.
It will have all of these things.
Then what is context engineering?
How to optimize this context
such that we can get better output
from the LLMs via agents.
That is what a simple thing context
engineering is.
The whole prompt that you built last
week lives in one box.
That is, we did prompt engineering,
right?
That prompt engineering will be in
this.
And remaining everything is
basically context engineering.
So now you all have a question in
your brain.
If you want to store so much
information in context,
why can't we just use the models
which has bigger context?
That's absolutely right.
Usually there are some models,
Gemini 3.5 Pro,
they support 1 million context guys,
1 million token context.
GPT 5.5, Claude Opus 4.8 or 4
.7.
But there are some smaller models
which has less context.
Let's say Claude Sonnet,
GPT 5 mini or LLaMA.
Now in the models with less context,
if you put a lot of information,
do you think they are going to work
properly?
No.
So it's not always that
you take a 1 million context model
and you fill up everything.
Then you are going to waste a lot of
tokens
and you are going to spend a lot of
money based on the tokens.
What should we do now?
We need to optimize how our agent's
performance works
based on the cost as well.
We are paying a lot of money for
these tokens.
We want as much optimized as
possible, right?
So what do we usually do?
We use smarter models to plan
everything.
After that, we use smaller models.
Let's say Sonnet or GPT 4 mini or 5
mini
to execute the task independently.
After that, we get all of this
information back.
That's how an agent would work.
So if you want to get a better
performance
then you need to understand
how you can properly optimize your
context
such that the agent works properly.
This is one more example of
why long context will not work
properly.
Let's say we have 1 million context.
You have filled that 1 million
context.
Then the model's performance will be
really bad
because it will tend to lose
information
because the context is completely
filled.
Usually, a model's performance is
always good
if the context is at 60 %
probably.
Because in the beginning,
it will not have any information
and until 50%, it is gaining a lot
of information
to achieve the task.
At this point, you get peak
performance.
After that, what do you think?
What if the context is not working
properly?
Then the performance will get
degraded
because it is overburdened with the
information.
So we want the context to be as much
optimized as possible.
Let's quickly look at what is the
difference
between prompt engineering and
context engineering.
Prompt engineering is a term for the
effort
needed to write your task in the
ideal format of an LLM chatbot.
But context engineering is the next
level of this.
It is about doing this autonomously
in a dynamic situation.
It takes more nuance and is
effectively the number one job
for the engineers building AI
agents.
So if you know how to optimize your
context properly,
then that is the most important
skill
that you need to have to build AI.
Do we
have any techniques to manage such
contexts?
Yes, there are four techniques.
One is prompt engineering,
because if it doesn't work, it won't
work.
Second, we have tools.
Third, we have rag and MCPs.
Fourth, we have compaction.
So what is prompt engineering?
At the end of the day,
the agent is also talking to the
LLM.
Then you need to have a better
designed prompt.
We saw how to define a better prompt
in the last video.
And the second thing is tools.
Let's assume this is a brain.
This brain is basically what we call
it as an LLM.
The brain doesn't do any work.
It needs to have legs and hands.
So giving legs and hands to this
LLM
is what we call it as tools.
That is, how to define a task
and how to do it properly.
Then this is where you put all the
definitions of the tools.
One of the examples is,
let's say you are on ChatGPT,
you have something called as web
search.
So what happens if you enable this?
It will instantly search the web by
default,
without you asking, and without it
automatically invoking.
If you enable this one,
maybe something called as create
images.
If you put it, the prompt will
automatically create images.
It doesn't need to think about it.
So you can create a lot of tools.
You can think of them like skills as
well,
but that's a different topic.
Let's not worry about that.
And then there is RAG and MCP.
What is RAG?
There is a big box,
that is what we call it as a
context.
In that context,
what is the information that you are
going to provide to the agent?
So the information is coming to me.
One of the best things is RAG,
if you have all the data that is
available with you,
which is also called as retrieval,
augmented generation.
You can connect to other platforms.
Let's say I want my agent to connect
to my Gmail.
Then that is how you will do MCPs,
which is called model context
protocol.
Model context
And then the next thing we have,
which is called as compaction.
It's basically,
let's say there are multiple agents
running parallel.
One, two, three, four.
And every agent has its own context
and every single thing.
This has an output,
this has an output,
this has an output.
What you will do is,
you will try to compress the output
from each of these agents
and then you create smaller
summarization.
You then orchestrate your next step.
So this is what we call it as a
compaction,
which is also called in the part of
memory.
So if you do these things,
then you can have multiple agents
running multiple times
at longer times without breaking it
properly.
So you need to understand what is
the best practice
of doing prompt engineering,
how you can define tools,
how you can build rag and MCPs,
and then how you can do compaction
to have an agent that can run
autonomously for you
for longer periods of time.
That's it, guys.
That is all everything you need to
know
regarding context engineering.
If you have learned something new
from this video,
please let me know in the comment
section.
And if you know someone who needs
this video,
please share it with them.
Thank you. Bye bye.